JAMES MACIUKENAS, PH.D.

Location: Evanston, IL | Phone: (773) 290-9947 | Email: <u>blueform@gmail.com</u> | LinkedIn: <u>linkedin.com/in/james-maciukenas</u>

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

Senior UX Researcher with 10+ years of research and design experience. Analyzes complex qualitative data to inform product decisions. Delivered results for Google, Amazon, universities, and non-profits. Eager to research the questions that help your decision-makers enrich the experiences of your users.

"James regularly delivered insights that were strongly appreciated by cross-functional stakeholders and influenced key product directions for our topic areas." –Blake Bennett, Senior UX Researcher for Gemini at Google

"[James's] blend of expertise, leadership, and client-centric focus makes him an invaluable asset to any organization fortunate enough to have him on board." – Erika Spear, Ph.D., Research Manager at AnswerLab

View case studies and work samples: moreperfectplaces.github.io

EXPERIENCE

Senior UX Researcher, AnswerLab, Chicago, IL & Remote, March 2022- March 2024

- Conducted a pivotal research initiative focused on the pre- and post-launch phases of a major tech industry leader's generative AI LLM
 chatbot. Provided actionable insights to design and engineering teams, leading to significant improvements in user experience.
- Completed over 50 qualitative studies using in-depth interviews, user testing, A/B testing, journey-mapping, and diary study methodologies to inform product development decisions for generative AI, digital assistant, search, and internal ad sales tools.
- Led foundational and iterative research for cross-functional teams making key product decisions, identifying opportunities, developing
 implementation plans, and optimizing Al-driven features.
- Contributed to the Emerging Tech Taskforce at AnswerLab developing best practices for generative AI usage within the company.

Web Developer, Indiana University-Bloomington, IN, 2019-2022

- Built accessible and user-friendly web applications that met UX and organization-defined design system standards.
- Swiftly transitioned processes online for the School of Public Health, mitigating pandemic challenges and ensuring service continuity while highlighting the Dean's thought leadership.

Web Developer and Designer, Illinois Institute of Technology, Chicago, IL, 2005-2019

- Led UX web development using A/B testing, market research, and analytics to guide stakeholders, resulting in a 40% increase in engagement and contributing to the college's first 7-figure donation.
- Designed and implemented a comprehensive design system, unifying the college's visual identity across online, print, and physical platforms, resulting in increased brand clarity and consistency.

Instructor, Illinois Institute of Technology, Chicago, IL, 2006-Present

• Designed and delivered curriculum on Public Engagement for Scientists; empowered 600+ students to effectively communicate complex scientific data, enhancing their ability to present research to diverse audiences and stakeholders.

VOLUNTEER EXPERIENCE

- Technical Advisor | Ordinary People International, NFP | Chicago, IL, 2011-Present
- Technical Advisor | Evanston AYSO (Community youth soccer) | Evanston, IL, 2015-2019

EDUCATION

- Ph.D., Technical Communication | Illinois Institute of Technology (IIT), Chicago, IL, May 2013
- M.S., Technical Communication and Information Design | IIT, Chicago, IL, May 2007
- B.F.A., Industrial Design | University of Illinois, Urbana-Champaign, May 1993

Strengths

Expert research skills, with a deep understanding of user needs; Excellent communication and moderation skills; Effective in high-pressure environments; Skilled in data analysis and visualization; Collaborative and supportive team player; Strong leadership and client-centric focus; Proactive emergent tools integration; Training & mentoring.

Skills

Remote & in-person user testing, UX writing, In-depth interviews, Survey development & deployment, Diary studies, Competitive analysis, Journey mapping, Analysis & reporting, Insight development, Client communications, Multimedia storytelling, Wireframing, Storyboarding, Data visualization, Web development, Design thinking

Tools

Adobe Creative Cloud: Illustrator, Photoshop, InDesign; Google Workspace: Sheets, Docs, Slides; Microsoft 365: Excel, Word, PowerPoint; Mural; dscout; Qualtrics; Figma; HTML & CSS; WordPress; Squarespace; Salesforce; Slack